CHAPTER 1

Introduction

Decoding Babasaheb
Ambedkar: Ideas and Praxis

This chapter is the outcome of a series of ‘Annual Ambedkar Memorial’ lectures delivered by the author at the University of British Columbia, Simon Fraser University, and York University, Canada, from 2 to 15 November 2017. It highlights the process of reductionism and erasure of Ambedkar across mainstream Indian academia and intelligentsia. The author makes an attempt here to highlight; on the one hand, that Ambedkar has been reduced only to a Dalit leader, knowingly or unknowingly. On the other hand, he has been erased from literature, sociology and history textbooks. Above all, he has also been ignored in the field of creative and artistic production. However, the chapter tries to decode Ambedkar by understanding various facets of his personality, thoughts and actions. Hence, the author explores the vast storage of Ambedkar’s objective and scientific knowledge, with its multiple shades.

Further, to deconstruct the aforesaid twin processes leading to the victimization of Ambedkar, we have also tried to probe how he has been getting accepted all over the world, especially by Western and American academia, researchers and the general public as well. Above all, drawing methodological legitimacy from a number of social scientists, we have tried to evolve a perspective that is, ‘a Perspective from Below’ and explain how personal experiences can produce reliable data that can be used to understand social reality.

There are two very important reasons why I have titled this chapter the way it is. These are: (a) The perspective of the article and second, (b) The process of reductionism and ‘erasure’ of Ambedkar and his ideas that have taken place in Indian society.

Let us first highlight some significant facts about the perspective of this chapter.

ACADEMIC LEGITIMACY AND
‘PERSPECTIVE FROM BELOW’

There can be several perspectives to understand Babasaheb Ambedkar. I have called my perspective, on the book, the Perspective From Below (Kumar 2018).

This is a perspective in which knowledge is produced by people who have their consciousness shaped out of their unique structural location at the lowest ebb of the Indian social order. This structural location is unique because it is due to this that they were forced to suffer from cumulative and collective exclusion. The former means that they are simultaneously excluded from social, economic, political, religious, educational, spatial, etc. spheres of life (ibid.). The term ‘collective’ here means that it is not one individual who suffers this exclusion; rather, the community as a whole suffers from exclusion. Further, their location has a bearing on the construction of consciousness, out of which the production of knowledge takes place (Kumar 2018: 57-78).

I have tried to establish this perspective on the basis of propositions laid down by various social scientists like Mills (1959), Berger and Luckmann (1967), Bourdieu (1986), Kuhn (1969), and Freire (1970). For instance, Mills (1959: 157) argues that ‘. . . problems of biography, of history and their interaction within social systems are coordinate points of the proper study of man . . . [and] . . . an integral part of sociological imagination’. Luckmann and Berger (1967: 4) argue that ‘sociology constitutes the sociological focus . . . on the existential determination of thought’. Bourdieu (1986: 16) has highlighted that ‘. . . accumulation of cultural capital . . . starts only for the offspring of families embodied with strong cultural capital and takes place through hereditary transmission’.

Integrating these three propositions together, we can show how biography, that is the lived experience of Dalits suffering from a unique type of social exclusion because of their structural location and exclusion from the mainstream social and cultural capital, shapes their consciousness out of which production of knowledge takes place. This chapter considers the aforesaid proposition in shaping the perspective of the author out of which this chapter is written.

Further, thinkers like Kuhn (1969) and Freire (1970) give academic legitimacy to Perspective From Below. Kuhn (1969) argues that research is not only done through data collection but it can be done by changing paradigms as well. Therefore, the Perspective From Below changes the paradigm for analysing Ambedkar’s thoughts and actions. First, it tries to understand the processes of reductionism and then deconstructs the established image of Ambedkar by providing a parallel discourse on Ambedkar’s thoughts and actions. It is in this context that this paper draws from Freire (1970), who has argued that ‘the pedagogy of the oppressed cannot be developed or practised by the oppressor’. According to him, it has to be developed by the oppressed himself. The oppressed, through this pedagogy, helps us to ‘. . . understand the causes of oppression’, and from this reflection, necessary engagement for liberation can be developed. Similarly, ‘Perspective From Below’ can help us to understand the erasures, reductionism and stigmatization of Babasaheb Ambedkar.

REDUCTIONISM AND ERASURE
OF AMBEDKAR

Having defined the perspective used in the chapter to understand reality, let me come to the second point, the issues of reductionism and erasure of Ambedkar. What exactly do I mean by the propositions—‘reductionism’ and ‘blackout’/‘erasure’ of Ambedkar? By reductionism, I mean that

(a) Ambedkar has been either understood only as a Dalit leader or as an intellectual who was only engaged with caste or annihilation of caste.

(b) Many intellectuals or journalists still doubt that Ambedkar was the chief architect of the Indian constitution.

(c) The third dimension of the process of reductionism is that the intellectuals and academia have not been able to recognize different shades of his thoughts and perspectives with which he has tried to understand the social realities of Indian and global society.

(d) The fourth dimension of reductionism is that the media and academia have failed to recognize the various stages and dynamics of his movements.

UNDERSTANDING REDUCTIONISM

Ambedkar has been reduced merely to a Dalit leader and an intellectual who was only engaged with the annihilation of caste. The first example comes from Eleanor Zelliot’s PhD dissertation, itself, in which she analysed Ambedkar’s movement from a particular caste perspective and as a leader of the Mahar caste. Her PhD thesis ‘Dr. Ambedkar and the Mahar Movement’. Zelliot has not even engaged with him as the leader of ex-untouchable communities as a whole. She did her work on Dalits in the early 1960s and submitted her thesis in 1969 (Zelliot 2004: Preface). It is difficult to understand why she could not appreciate the larger canvas of Ambedkar’s thought and philosophy, his role as leader of a number of movements and chief architect of the Indian constitution. Perhaps, that is why she herself wrote, ‘I was never satisfied that I had done justice to Dr Ambedkar. . . . The unfortunate title prompted the idea that Ambedkar was only a Mahar leader’ (ibid: Preface).

Arun Shourie, considered to be then one of India’s topmost journalists and went on to become a cabinet minister in Vajpayee’s government, published a book titled, Worshipping the False God: Ambedkar, and the Facts Which Have Been Erased to prove his point that Ambedkar was not the chief architect of the Indian constitution. He was only a rapporteur. In his own words,

. . . the Constitution came to be framed—by the collective, iterative deliberations of a very large number. Ambedkar was one of these members. In some ways, he played an important part. But his job was really that of a rapporteur, not that of one who set policy, certainly not that of the creator (Shourie 1997, 2012: 449-50).

Shourie further stigmatized Ambedkar by arguing that ‘The legacy of Ambedkar is a country with a deepened sense of shame in its entire past. And thereby disabled’ (Shourie 1997, 2012: 381). Another example of reductionism comes as late as 2014. This time, a literary personality, Arundhati Roy (2014), in her effort to popularize Ambedkar’s writings, could not see beyond Ambedkar’s Annihilation of Caste as his most valuable contribution. The reductionism can be further substantiated by the point that her introduction was more voluminous than Ambedkar’s text, Annihilation of Caste.

The worst and almost ‘blasphemous’ statement of reductionism and stigmatization of Ambedkar comes from the history book Bharat Ka Mukti Sangram (Indian Liberation War) by Ayodhya Singh. The book was a popular reading of its time for two reasons. One, it was published by an established and reputed publisher. Second, it ran in many editions and several reprints. For instance, its first edition came in 1977, the second in 1992, and third in 2003. In between there were three reprints of the book in 1987, 1994, and 1996 as well. The introduction of the writer on the back page of the book says that he was a journalist, writer, and freedom fighter. He was associated with a very progressive magazine, Saptahik Swadhinta (Weekly Freedom), published in Calcutta. His most famous book includes Hindustan ka Swadhinta Aandolan aur Communist (India’s Freedom Movement and Communist). Let us see what a so-called intellectual has to say about Ambedkar.

Singh writes that Ambedkar . . . Baroda ke Raja aur Mahar jaati ki achhut kanya ke Putra the . . .Vah maldar aur jamindar Harijanon ke drishtikon ka pratinidhitv karte the Ambedkar ne jo gyapan commission (simon) ke samne pesh kiya tha vah angrej parasth tha (Singh 2003: 459-60). Ambedkar was the son of the King of Baroda and daughter of Mahar caste . . . he used to represent the view of affluent and feudal Harijans. The memorandum which Ambedkar presented before the commission (Simon) was pro-British—Author’s translation.

The moot question is how someone can write about such a famous personality, and that too as late as the 1970s when so much was already written about him and he had occupied a number of national positions and had launched a number of mass movements for the downtrodden. The worst is that he has gone unchallenged to this date.

The misunderstanding about the real identity and status of Ambedkar has always existed. Look at what Kumar (2005: 514) had to say,

Gandhiji, after discussing the problems of Dalits with Ambedkar, asked Mahadev Desai why Ambedkar told him that he (Ambedkar) did not have a motherland. Desai explained that it was because Ambedkar was an ‘untouchable’. Gandhiji was surprised to learn this, and he told Desai that he had thought Ambedkar was a conscientious Brahmin who spoke for the untouchables. . . . Even as late as 1999, a high-profile university professor of sociology, who has extensively worked on the issues related to caste, asked me, ‘What is the difference between Jai Shree Ram and Jai Bheem, as both are religious symbols?’ I had to explain to the learned professor that this Jai Bheem is not the Bheem of Mahabharat; it comes from the first name of Bheemrao Ambedkar, which has now become the greeting symbol of Dalits and other marginalized groups in India and across the globe.

UNDERSTANDING AMBEDKAR’S ERASURE

Provided a few examples to prove the point of how Ambedkar has been the victim of ‘reductionism’, let us take a certain examples to prove the point of his erasures. As far as the proposition erasure is concerned, I want to argue that, on the one hand, he has been erased from pioneering literary, sociological texts and texts on Indian history; on the other hand, he has also been erased from visual and artistic works. However, at this point in time, because of lack of resources, it is difficult to ascertain whether these erasures are by design or by default.

The first literary text from which Babasaheb Ambedkar has been completely erased is Mulk Raj Anand’s novel Untouchable (1935). In this text, Gandhiji is hailed as the emancipator of untouchables. It is a fact that by the time Anand had written his text, Ambedkar had already arrived on the horizon of the emancipation of Dalits, and he already had a steady movement for the upliftment of Dalits. However, Anand has completely ignored Ambedkar’s social, political, educational, and religious movements for ameliorating Dalits from their wretched condition.

As far as erasure from academic texts is concerned, there are several examples from this sphere. However, the first text in question is G.S. Ghurye’s Caste and Race in India first published in 1932. The book was published one and a half decades after Ambedkar’s Caste in India: Their Mechanism, Genesis and Development, published in the Antiquary Journal. However, Ghurye takes cognizance of Ambedkar’s writings on caste only once (Ghurye 1932: 216-17). The Case of Louis Dumont’s Homo Hierarchicus, first published in the 1970s with several publications thereafter, is different. In this book, Ambedkar’s work has not been cited even once. Several other sociologists have worked on caste extensively, but have not taken note of Ambedkar’s works like—Caste in India: Their Mechanism, Genesis and Development (Ambedkar 1979), Annihilation of Caste (Ambedkar 1979), Who Were the Shudras? (Ambedkar 1990(c)), The Untouchables: Who Were They and Why They Became Untouchables? (Ambedkar 1990(c)), etc. Based on the academic arguments contained in the aforesaid Ambedkar’s works, it can be easily argued that any analysis of caste without these works would be incomplete.

The third example of the erasure of Ambedkar can be witnessed in the influential history text by Bipan Chandra et al. (1989). This book is running in a number of editions. I have seen its seventh edition. That means the book is widely circulated and has made an impact on people’s minds. In this book, with 600 pages (including bibliography and index), Ambedkar’s name appears first time on page number 291 and then on pages 293-4, 336 and 364. Out of these five times where Ambedkar’s name appears, to begin with, on page 291, Ambedkar is referred in passing with reference to Gandhi’s fast-unto-death. On this page, Bipan Chandra writes, ‘Political leaders of different political party persuasions, including Madan Mohan Malviya, M.C. Rajah and Ambedkar, now became active’. On page 293, he again refers to Ambedkar’s name with reference to Gandhi. In the words of Chandra, ‘ . . . he was not hostile to Dr. Ambedkar and other Harijans who criticized and distrusted him’.

Similarly, on page 294, Chandra analyses that, ‘he disagreed with Ambedkar when the latter asserted that ‘the outcaste is a byproduct of the caste system’. On page 336 he is referred to indirectly through his followers. Chandra (1989: 336) writes, ‘In Bombay, the AITUC, the Communists and the followers of Dr. B.R. Ambedkar organized a strike on 7 November 1938, in seventeen out of seventy-seven textile mills against the passage of the Industrial Dispute Act’. He doesn’t even acknowledge that Ambedkar had, by that time, become a force to reckon with and had established his ‘Independent Labour Party’ and contested elections. Last but not least, on page 364, Ambedkar is referred to in passing in the following words,

The situation soon began to take an ugly turn, with hostile demonstrations by Rajputs and Muslims during Gandhiji’s prayer meetings, and Mohammad Ali Jinnah’s and Ambedkar’s demand that the Muslims and Depressed Classes be given separate representation.

It is astonishing to note that on all five occasions, Ambedkar’s name appears in the book only as a passing reference without any independent agency. In doing so, Chandra et al. (1989) not only ignore Ambedkar’s pioneering work, Pakistan or The Partition of India, first published in 1940, and its second edition came in 1945. The historians argue that this was the only book-length answer to the solution to the problem of Pakistan (Anderson 2012, Kumar 2012). Not only that, Chandra also ignored Ambedkar’s contribution to the Constituent Assembly, his role as the Chairman of the Drafting Committee and his role in several other subcommittees of the Indian Constitution. In this way, Ambedkar’s erasure from the history textbooks is glaring and has reduced him merely as a Dalit leader.

ERASURE FROM WORK OF CREATIVE FIELD

We have discussed so far how Ambedkar has been erased in academic texts let us now analyse how he has been erased even from artistic and creative fields like feature films. Ambedkar was completely erased from Richard Attenborough’s directed film, Gandhi, released in 1982. This movie is an epic and historical film, and is regularly shown on Indian television on the birth and death anniversaries of M.K. Gandhi or on any other occasion of national festivals.

The feature film was nominated for Academy and Oscar awards. Gandhi received a leading nominations in eleven categories and won the awards in eight categories, including Best Feature Film and Best Director Award. However, in this film, Ambedkar was totally erased. However, it is a fact that Gandhi picked up the removal of untouchability as one of the agendas of his movement after the 1930s because of his conflict with Ambedkar. Gandhi’s tug of war with Ambedkar at the Round Table Conference in London, his fast unto death against Separate Electorates to Dalits, signing of the famous Poona Pact in September 1932, and then Gandhi and Ambedkar dialogue on Annihilation of Caste (Ambedkar 1979), are all highly publicized episodes of Gandhi’s life which remain fresh and not easy to be obliterated from public memory. Yet, these episodes where Ambedkar would have appeared prominently have been erased completely from the film.

In this context, one may ask why one should mention Ambedkar in the autobiographical feature film on Gandhi. The erasure of Ambedkar in Gandhi assumes a serious proposition because when Jabbar Patel made a feature film on Ambedkar in the year 2000, Gandhi was present in the film very prominently. Therefore, a contestable question emerges in this context—If Ambedkar had no relevance to Gandhi, then how come Gandhi becomes relevant in a film on the life of Ambedkar? Hence, this raises serious doubts. Is there a deliberate attempt to erase Ambedkar in the film on Gandhi? Why can’t he be shown in the film beside Gandhi? A corollary to that is, can Ambedkar be analysed independently on his own without any reference to Gandhi?

HOW CAN WE DECODE AMBEDKAR’S
REDUCTIONISM AND ERASURE?

If these are a few examples to prove the point that there is a general pattern of ‘Reductionism’ and erasure of Ambedkar, one can ask if there are a few more reasons based on which we can argue that there exist processes of reductionism and erasure of Ambedkar in Indian society. Here again, we can highlight at least five reasons based on which we can argue that Ambedkar has been a victim of processes of reductionism and erasure. These reasons are:

(a) The way Ambedkar has been revered by his followers and supporters.

(b) The way he was appreciated by Columbia University while receiving an honorary L.L.D. degree in the year 1952.

(c) The way in which Western social scientists have engaged with his academic acumen and the way he has become visible at the international level.

(d) The horizon, shades, epistemologies, and approaches with which Ambedkar has produced his knowledge.

(e) The nature and dynamics of his movements.

Let us briefly take these facts one-by-one to prove the point. At the outset, we understand the dimensions of Ambedkar’s personality, which his followers highlight and revere. His followers address him as Vishva Vibhooti (global icon), Bodhisattva (like Buddha), Bharat Ratna (Indian gem after the highest civilian award of the country was conferred upon him), Samvidhan Nirmata (framer of the constitution) ‘Babasaheb Dr. B.R. Ambedkar’. That means he is revered as a spiritual leader who has achieved a higher status of Bodhisattva by treading the path of Buddha and practicing the same. Second, these addresses also highlight his higher civilian achievement in Indian society, where he was conferred the country’s highest civilian award, Bharat Rattan (gem of India).

The supporters deliberately add the epithet in front of his name, Dr. to highlight his educational achievement, which he had at that point in time without any other being near to him. His followers affectionately call him ‘Babasaheb’. Apart from this, he is also revered as the maker of the Indian constitution (Bharat ke Samvidhan Nirmata). Last, but not least, he is also being addressed as ‘Global Icon’ (Vishva Vibhuti). This is the repertoire of his aura highlighted by his followers, which count in millions, yet he is reduced only to a Dalit leader by the mainstream media, academia, or intelligentsia. That is why they feel that he is not given the respect that is due to him.

REFLECTIONS BY EDUCATIONAL
INSTITUTION

If this is the informal way in which Ambedkar is revered by his followers, let us observe how he is referred to by an educational formal institution. For instance, how did the Columbia University refer him while awarding an honorary degree some fifty-nine years back on 5 June 1952. The citation letter described him in the following words:

Bhimrao Ramji Ambedkar LL.D. . . . for three years a graduate student in this university, receiving the doctorate in Political Science; subsequently a student of the Inns of Court and the University of London, obtaining a doctorate in economics; for the past three decades a barrister, university professor . . . as a framer of the constitution . . . one of India’s leading citizens . . . a great social reformer and a valiant upholder of human rights. (L.L.D. Citation, Columbia University, see Annexure I on page 129).

In the same vein, we should also take into account how a few Western social scientists have highlighted Ambedkar’s achievements in the sphere of higher education in comparison to other leaders of that time. Let us see these lines:

Gandhi did not claim much book learning . . . Nehru, on the other hand, had enjoyed higher education Gandhi lacked . . . it would be unfair to compare Nehru to Ambedkar, intellectually head and shoulder above most of the Congress leaders, in part due to far more serious training . . . at LSE and Columbia, to read who is to enter a different world (Anderson 2012: 51-2).

Another significant appreciation by a foreign dignitary came from Edwina Mountbatten, wife of the last Viceroy of India Lord Mountbatten, when she wrote a congratulatory letter to Ambedkar on his appointment as the chairman of the drafting committee of the Indian Constitution. Edwina argued, ‘I am personally glad to see you supervising the Constitution’. She was so much impressed with Ambedkar that she emphasised, ‘. . . you are the only genius who can give equal justice to every caste and creed’ (see Annexure II on page 130). Last but not least, believing in Ambedkar’s brillance and patriotism, she accentuated, ‘I have been your long time admirer and hoping you will fulfill your duty towards the country’ (ibid.).

AMBEDKAR AND ENGAGEMENT OF
WESTERN SCHOLARS

Apart from taking cognizance of his academic credentials, Anderson also took note of his political foresight during India’s struggle for independence. According to Anderson, when Gandhi, Nehru, the whole Congress and even the Muslim League did not have a clue about the outcome of India’s struggle for independence, Ambedkar alone had a solution to the Hindu-Muslim conflict. Anderson (2012: 89) argues that:

Only outside Congress was there lucidity. Predictably, of those who would go on to construct the Indian state, Ambedkar alone was early on clear-sighted enough to see that self-determination could not be denied Muslims if they wanted it, and to propose a rational solution for it. In 1944, at a time when the very idea of it was taboo in Congress, and still little more than a vague slogan in the Muslim League itself, he published the only serious work on the issue that would determine the outcome of the struggle for independence. Pakistan or Partition of India, whose references range from Renan to Acton to Carson, from Canada to Ireland to Switzerland, stands as a devastating indictment of the intellectual poverty of Congress and its leaders. Critical to the Muslim introversion, alert to Savarkar’s Hindutva, contemptuous of the myth of pan-religious amity, Ambedkar did not advocate separation of the two communities, but he proposed referenda to determine popular wishes and in the event that Muslims insisted on it, sketch the boundaries he thought might ensue. After partition, he would call for a division of Kashmir to allow its Muslim-majority zone, including the valley to join Pakistan.

In the same vein, Cosimo Zene (ed. 2013) has tried to compare the political philosophies of Antonio Gramsci and Ambedkar. The volume, which includes contributions of at least fourteen social scientists belonging to various parts of the world, is testimony to the fact that Ambedkar’s larger ideas are being recognized and compared with other philosophers of the world. The book has an interdisciplinary approach. If Ambedkar is the owner of such high academic, social, political and educational credentials, according to Western scholars, then the mainstream media, intelligentsia, and academia in India have not been able to recognize his greatness and have reduced him to the status of a Dalit leader only. Have they willfully erased him, or is it by default? Hence, this book, on the one hand, attempts to deconstruct the established image of Ambedkar and, on the other, records his real contributions in the field of knowledge production. Further, it maps his accomplishments through different shades of movements launched by him at different intervals.

AMBEDKAR’S VISIBILITY AT THE
INTERNATIONAL LEVEL

It is surprising Ambedkar’s visibility has grown at the international level. This is evident from his bust being installed at Columbia University; London School of Economics, London; Simon Fraser University; York University; Brandeis University, Boston; Massachusetts Amherst, USA; Melbourne University and Western Sydney University, Australia; Koyasan University, Japan and a Ambedkar’s statue at the Buddhist Research Institute, Vietnam. The visibility has been further highlighted by the institution of lecture series and memorial lectures in his name at various universities of the world: Manchester Metropolitan University, UK; Calgary University; University of British Columbia; Simon Fraser University; and York University in Canada; and Columbia University, New York, USA (data collected during fieldwork). Last but not least, the Ambedkar Chair in Indian Constitutional Law has been established at Columbia University, USA.

Apart from his visibility at the international level through educational institutions, the social celebrations and establishment of international organizations in the Dalit diaspora all over the world have reinforced his visibility at the international level (Kumar 2013). The Dalit diaspora has forced the international community to recognize his larger contributions to the emancipation of the downtrodden and championing of their human rights. On the basis of the above empirical evidence, one is forced to say that Ambedkar has gradually transcended national boundaries to occupy the status of a global icon.

DIFFERENT SHADES OF THOUGHTS
OF AMBEDKAR

It is in this context that we would also like to highlight Ambedkar’s various shades of thoughts present in his writings and speeches. This will help us to decode Ambedkar’s larger ideas. Methodologically, we could evolve a scope of knowledge with which he was engaged during his lifetime. We can observe at least ten shades of thoughts in his writings and speeches published during his lifetime and posthumously. These are social (Ambedkar 1979, 1987(c)(b)), political (Ambedkar 1990(c), 1991(a)), economic (Ambedkar 1989), religious (1987(a), 1992), gender (Ambedkar 1987(c)(e)), educational (Ambedkar 1982), legal and constitutional (Ambedkar 1994), developmental (Ambedkar 1987(c), 1991(a)), on human rights (1979) specific to the marginalized. This is only a suggestive list, and one can find a number of other shades of thought in his writings and speeches published by the Maharashtra government posthumously.

EPISTEMOLOGY OF AMBEDKAR’S THOUGHT

Ambedkar did not produce knowledge on a speculative basis; rather, he produced empirical knowledge. His empirical knowledge has three main foundations. The first source is the influence of Buddha, Kabir, and Phule. The second basis is his personal experiences from childhood exclusion, experience of freedom, equality and enlightened background of foreign universities to experiences as members of various kinds of public offices. It is important to emphasize that personal experiences have a significant impact on the production of knowledge and can be treated as social scientific data (Mills 1959, Luckman and Berger 1967, Freire 1970). Particularly it is noteworthy to emphasize what Mills (1959) has to say about the significance of biography as far as sociological imagination is concerned, out of which the production of knowledge takes place.

According to Mills, he is not merely concerned with external biography, which is associated with a sequence of social roles; rather, he is interested in understanding biography with reference to the institutions in which an individual plays a role. According to him, ‘Such a view requires us to understand the most internal and psychological features of man: in particular his self-image and his conscience and indeed the very growth of mind’ (Mills 1959: 179). Therefore, personal influences and experiences become a source and foundation of knowledge and basically an authentic source of knowledge.

A third source of foundation of Ambedkar’s knowledge depends on empirical sources. These are at least eight types of sources of data. These included archaeological sources, Indological sources, government reports and other documents, reports of commissions and committees, newspaper clippings, books and journals, personal observation and people’s perception, and discussions with members of the society. Again, there are a number of permutations and combinations of these sources in the production of knowledge by Ambedkar (collated from Dr Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, specifically from vol. 1 to 13).

PERSPECTIVE AND APPROACHES
TO KNOWLEDGE

Apart from different shades of thoughts and epistemology of knowledge, we can observe that Ambedkar had adopted multiple approaches to producing his knowledge. We can observe at least four approaches in his writings. These are civilizational (Ambedkar 1987(c)), historical (Ambedkar 1979, 1990(b)), evolutionary (Ambedkar 1990(b) 1992) and comparative approaches (Ambedkar 1979, 1989(c)) for the production of knowledge. To take one example to prove the point, for instance, while understanding religion in India, he began by tracing the origin of different civilizations. He then differentiated between religion and theology. He also used Müller, Durkheim, Weber, etc., to understand the meaning of religion in tribal society and modern societies.

Having discussed the perspective of the book in this chapter, the process of reductionism and the erasure of Ambedkar’s larger ideas, thoughts and philosophy, we have analysed four added facts on the basis of which we can argue that there exists a process of reductionism and erasure, of him. These are denials of taking cognizance of the ways he has been revered by his followers, how institutions have appreciated his personality and deeds, how various social scientists have understood his contributions. Last, but not least, they have not taken note of the different shades, epistemology, and perspectives with which Ambedkar has produced his knowledge. Instead of engaging with such a vast canvas of his methodologically produced objective and scientific knowledge, the Indian origin social scientists have reduced him to an individual who has written only on caste or to only a leader of Dalits.

DIFFERENT STAGES AND PHASES OF
BABASAHEB’S MOVEMENTS

AMBEDKAR: THE SOCIAL REFORMER

There is a tendency among scholars and laymen alike to reduce Ambedkar’s movement as an undifferentiated monolithic whole. However, if we analyse his activities a little bit closely, we can easily divide Babasaheb’s movement into five different yet interrelated stages/phases. These phases were complementary and supplementary to his efforts for achieving equality, liberty, fraternity, and justice not only for the Dalits but for other social groups in general, and Indian society, in particular (see Kumar 2002). Each phase enriched his experience in fighting against the existing inequalities of the Hindu social order. The periodization of his leadership is also necessary to understand the rational of his changing socio-political stances in his long struggle.

The first phase began in early 1919 when he gave a memorandum to the franchise commission asking for self-representation of Dalits, and this continued till 1930s. During this period, he acted more like a social reformer while fighting against the rigid caste system and its draconian practice of untouchability. He was convinced by the knowledge of world history that ‘history bears out the proposition that political revolutions have always been preceded by social and religious revolutions’, which is why he launched various types of social movements.

To begin with, Ambedkar formed a society, the Bahishkrit Hitkarini Sabha (Organization for the Interest of the Excluded), to serve the interests of outcastes on 20 July 1924, which could place their social and political problems before the government. Second, in this phase, he launched Mahad Satyagraha (Mahad is a place in Maharashtra and Satyagraha means peaceful sit in movement) to take water from a public tank. Another unique event that took place during the Mahad Satyagraha was the burning of the Manusmriti (sacred text by Manu who codified the social laws of the society), the sacred law book of the Hindus. Justifying his action of burning the Manusmriti, Ambedkar said in the 3 February 1928 issue of his Bahishkrit Bharat that his reading of the Manusmriti ‘had convinced him that it was abusive and insulting in its treatment of the Shudras and it did not even remotely support the idea of social equality. To burn a thing was to register protest against the idea it represented.’ In the same vein, in this phase, Ambedkar organized the largest and longest satyagraha on 2 March 1930 at Nasik for the Dalits’ entry to the Kala Rama Temple (in this temple, the statue of Rama is black in colour). Around 15,00 Mahars and Chambhars had assembled at Nasik. But the temple had to be closed for about a year to keep them away from entering it. The Parvati Satyagraha in Poona also met the same fate.

Although Ambedkar was leading a movement for temple entry, he never wanted to enter them in the real sense of the term. In his own words,

I did not launch the temple entry movement because I wanted the Depressed Classes to become worshippers of idols that they were prevented from worshipping or because I believed that temple entry would make them equal members in and an integral part of Hindu society. So far as this aspect of the case is concerned, I would advise the Depressed Classes to insist upon a complete overhauling of Hindu society and Hindu theology before they consent to become an integral part of Hindu society. I started temple entry Satyagraha only because I felt that was the best way of energizing the Depressed Classes and making them conscious of their position. As I believe I have achieved that, therefore, I have no more use for temple entry. I want the Depressed Classes to concentrate their energy and resources on politics and education (Zelliot 1992: 131).

AMBEDKAR: THE POLITICAL LEADER

The second phase started in 1930 and ended with his joining the Constituent Assembly. During this period, he acted more like a political leader, emphasizing the need to establish the fundamental rights of the Dalits, acquire their political rights and establish a few political parties to realize these political rights. For instance, defining the interests and rights of the Dalits, Ambedkar opined,

The untouchables are usually regarded as objects of pity but they are ignored in any political scheme on the score that they have no interest to protect. And yet their interests are the greatest. Not that they have large property to protect from confiscation. But they have their very persona confiscated (Ambedkar 1979: 255).

The socio-religious disabilities have dehumanized the untouchables, and their interests at stake are, therefore the interests of humanity. The interests of property are nothing before such primary interests. . . . The untouchable is not even a citizen. Citizenship is a bundle of rights such as: (1) personal liberty, (2) personal security, (3) right to hold private property, (4) equality before the law, (5) liberty of conscience, (6) freedom of opinion and speech, (7) right to assembly, (8) right of representation in a country’s government and (9) right to hold office under the State . . . These are the interests of the untouchables (Ambedkar 1979: 255-6).

Second, during this phase, he also went on to participate in the Round Table Conference in London and won the ‘Separate Electorate’ for the Dalits. The latter gave Dalits the power of two votes. Through one vote, they would elect their own caste representatives, and in another one, they could elect the general caste representative. This was unique because it gave them their true representative. However, Gandhi, as the representative of the Indian National Congress, did not accept the separate electorate for the Dalits and went on to fast unto death. This led Ambedkar to enter into a pact called the ‘Poona Pact’ in September 1932. Responding to the fast unto death of Gandhi, Ambedkar issued a press statement on Gandhi’s fast to expose his tactics, ‘suffice it is to say that although Mr Gandhi declared a fast unto death, he did not want to die. He wanted very much to live’ (Ambedkar 1991(a): 88).

Further, Ambedkar argued that the fast created a problem of how to save Gandhi’s life. All eyes turned on Ambedkar for the same. To this, Ambedkar reflected,

As to myself it is no exaggeration to say that no man was placed in a greater and graver dilemma than I was then. It was a baffling situation. I had to make a choice between two different alternatives. There was before me the duty, which I owed as a part of common humanity, to save Gandhi from sure death. There was before me the problem of saving for the untouchables the political rights, which the Prime Minister had given them. I responded to the call of humanity and saved the life of Mr Gandhi by agreeing to alter the Communal Award in manner satisfactory to Mr Gandhi (Ambedkar 1991(a): 88).

After the Poona Pact, separate electorates were converted to ‘Joint Electorates’, which exists even today. Despite this fact, Ambedkar had an impact on independent political rights for the Dalits because of which they could represent themselves in politics. With this achievement, Ambedkar formed the Independent Labour Party in 1936, contested the Bombay Assembly elections and won several seats. The elections gave him and Dalits new confidence, and in 1942, he launched the All India Scheduled Caste Federation to broaden his national political base. During this phase, he had a discussion and later exchanged words with Ram Manohar Lohia to launch a united political party (Lohia 1964: 31-2). However, Ambedkar could not do so because of his untimely death on 6 December 1956. But he was quite successful in laying the foundation of the Republican Party of India, which was formed in 1957 after his mahaparinirvana (death in Pali language).

In his political party, Ambedkar also established a women’s wing and used to have regular and simultaneous sessions along with the main political party and used to address women cadres. He groomed many women leaders in his party who later on went on to become Members of the Legislative Assembly. Such was Ambedkar’s politics. He never mixed religion with politics, and tried to mobilize people in politics on a secular basis.

THE CHIEF ARCHITECT OF THE
INDIAN CONSTITUTION

The third phase of Ambedkar’s movement started in 1946 when he entered the Constituent Assembly and became the chairman of the Drafting Committee. Ambedkar’s entrance into the Constituent Assembly, even against his will, is regarded as the third phase of his leadership in the sphere of Dalit amelioration. As the chairman of the Drafting Committee, Ambedkar bore the burden of not only drafting the various democratic principles but also of defending them clause by clause in the Constituent Assembly debates. The Constituent Assembly worked for two years, eleven months and seventeen days since it first met on 9 December 1946. That means Ambedkar had to be present on all these days. Further, in this regard, one can make out the amount of labour and time he had to put into preparing the constitution by his following reflection.

Ambedkar argued that the draft constitution, as prepared by the constitutional adviser, was a text for the Drafting Committee to work upon, consisting of 243 Articles and thirteen Schedules. In its final form, the draft constitution contained 395 Articles and eight Schedules. The total number of amendments to the draft constitution tabled was approximately 7,635. Of them, the total number of amendments actually moved in the house was over 2,473 (Ambedkar 1994: 1206). That means he read all the 7,635 amendments, discarded 5,162 amendments and incorporated 2,473 amendments to produce our constitution, a herculean task with extraordinary intellect (ibid.).

The members of the Constituent Assembly have accepted the amount of labour, both intellectual and physical, that was put in by Ambedkar in the preparation of the final shape of the Constitution of India. For instance, praising Ambedkar’s contribution, T.T. Krishnamachari, one of the senior members of the Constituent Assembly from the then Madras Presidency, opined in the assembly that,

Mr President Sir, I am one of those in the house who have listened to Dr. Ambedkar very carefully. I am aware of the amount of work and enthusiasm that he has brought to bear on the work of drafting this constitution. . . . The house is perhaps aware that of the seven members nominated by you, one had resigned from the house and was replaced. One died and was not replaced. One was in America and his place was not filled up and another person was engaged in state affairs and there was a void to that extent. One or two people were away from Delhi and perhaps reasons of health did not permit them to attend. So, it ultimately happened that the burden of drafting this Constitution fell on Dr. Ambedkar and I have no doubt that we are grateful to him for having achieved this task in a manner that is undoubtedly commendable (Ambedkar 1994: 72).

This is the contribution of Ambedkar in the making of the Indian constitution and yet people are not ready to accept his contributions.

Further, during the third epoch, he also joined the Nehru cabinet and became the first law minister of independent India but resigned in October 1951. In his capacity as law minster of the country, Babasaheb wanted to bring into law what he had titled the ‘Hindu Code Bill’ to empower Hindu women as a whole. The bill was envisaged to secure a dignified and equal status for Hindu women with a number of clauses. There were rights of inheritance and maintenance. There were laws against dowry. Instead of polygamy, monogamy was made legal. The Hindu marriage became a contract instead of a sacrament. The consent of the wife was to be made compulsory in the event of adoption. He had also mooted that, like son, wife and daughter should be given a share in the property of husband and father, respectively. Ambedkar, in his proposed Hindu Code Bill, attempted to ‘consolidate the different categories of stridhan into a single category of property and lay down the uniform rule of succession’ (Ambedkar 1995: 7). We will further elaborate on this fact in Chapter 4 of this book.

AMBEDKAR: THE RELIGIOUS RENOUNCER

In the fourth phase of his leadership (1952-6), Babasaheb emerged as a renouncer and religious leader. He started mobilizing his supporters to embrace Buddhism and finally returned to its fold on 14 October 1956 before attaining nirvana on 6 December 1956. Ambedkar’s conversion to Buddhism has been criticized as a political act. Again, it is a case of the reductionism of his larger vision. Zelliot has replied very aptly to such critics. She argued,

‘What possible political advantage does conversion offer?’ Conversion to Buddhism immediately cuts off . . . deserving governmental benefits . . . to Untouchable castes. Ambedkar’s delayed conversion came long after the period of combining the conversion idea with political expediency, and by then reference to the conversion as a political threat had lost its significance. Instead, it had reference to the great Asian Buddhist world, the reputation of Buddhism as an important religion both in India and the West and the possibility of Buddhism as a moral force (Zelliot 1992: 195).

We are aware of the fact that Babasaheb was well aware of the ‘Sciences of Religion’ and had a deep understanding of different religions of the world. He had meaningfully engaged and interpreted scholars like Müller, Weber, and Durkheim on religion. That is why he could differentiate between theology and rituals as two parts of the religion. However, he was convinced about the necessity of religion in the society. According to him, religion is the most significant institution which performs the most significant role of social control. The law cannot have full control in the society. That is why he argued that religion is very essential for the Dalits as well. However, according to him, religion should be egalitarian in nature.

That is why when he got the opportunity, he chose Buddhism because he was of the opinion that it was based on egalitarian principles like equality, liberty, and fraternity (Ambedkar 2003: 503). Second, there is no mediator between God and people. People can be their own guides. There is no church and no idea of soul and rebirth (Ambedkar 1992: 250-59). Hence, Buddha’s gospel would be the most effective ideology of emancipation for the Dalits who need psychological and social uplift; that is why instead of Hinduism, Ambedkar chose Buddhism as the religion for the emancipation of Dalits.

Ambedkar, after conversion, was called to participate at the World Buddhist Conference from 15-16 November 1956. Ambedkar’s last effort was to popularize the Buddhist faith in India. Therefore, he wrote a full-length book Buddha and His Dhamma. He tried to explain the tenets of Buddhism in this book in the most simple language for the common masses and tried to eliminate the confusion created by Brahmanical interpretation, which had intruded into Buddha’s life. In the Introduction of this book, Ambedkar has argued that he has given ‘. . . a clear and consistent statement of the life and teachings of the Buddha’ (Ambedkar 1992).

AMBEDKAR THE EDUCATOR

Apart from these four shades, there is a fifth shade of his movement, which cuts across all four stages/phases of his movements and is the phase in which he acts as an educator. Who can forget Ambedkar’s famous slogan, ‘Educate, Agitate and Organize’ (Ambedkar 2003: 276), which he gave in ‘The All-India Depressed Classes’ conference held at Nagpur from 18-20 July 1942. He reiterated the same slogan in 1945 at the annual conference as ‘The All India Scheduled Castes Federation’ (Ambedkar 1979: 357). This slogan has been accepted by the Dalit masses as a guiding principle to motivate them to take education as a tool of their emancipation.

During this period, he brought out at least five newspapers to educate his people regarding the tyrannies and oppression to which Dalits were subjected. The first newspapers were Mook Nayak (Hero of the Voiceless), started in 1920, Bahishkrit Bharat (Ex-communicated Indians) started in 1927 till 1929, Samata (Equality) started in 1928, Janata (The People) started in 1930, and last but not the least Prabuddha Bharat (The Enlightened Indian) started in February 1956. Through these newspapers, he wanted to awaken the downtrodden masses from their age-old lethargy and inaction and unite them.

Ambedkar also helped and motivated regional wings of his political parties to publish newspapers. For instance, in 1945, the Bengal Provincial Scheduled Caste Federation, associated with a national political party, the All India Scheduled Caste Federation, started the People’s Herald newspaper from Calcutta. Speaking on the inaugural function of the newspaper, Ambedkar emphasized, ‘A newspaper is . . . one means of educating people’ (Ambedkar 2003: 348).

As far as formal education is concerned, he asked the government to grant concessions, scholarships and other facilities to Dalit students. During this phase, he founded the People’s Education Society in Bombay in 1945. In 1946, he established the Siddharth College of Arts and Science to provide basic and non-discriminatory scientific education to Dalits and others.

CONCLUSION

On the basis of the above discussion, we can conclude that the mainstream academia, intelligentsia, and media have been, knowingly or unknowingly, involved in the process of reductionism, erasure, and stigmatization of Ambedkar, among his followers across the globe. These triple processes are evident in the above discussions, which have been substantiated on the basis of empirical data. We have observed them in the history, sociology, literary texts, and books produced by journalists. Even in the creative fields like film, the erasure of Ambedkar is so glaring. Not only that, there prevails a lot of misunderstandings around his real identity.

However, we have observed that these processes can be deconstructed with the help of empirical data collected with a perspective called consistency ‘the Perspective from Below’. The data from this perspective has been collected both from India and across the world. The data portrays Ambedkar in a very different light and proves the point that his acceptance at the international level is growing day by day. If we engage with this data, we have observed that it created a totally new discourse. This discourse portrays Ambedkar as an academician who has engaged with social realities concerning our nation and the globe. That is why the social scientists of the world are engaging with him, and the institutions are having his busts along with his books. That is why it is pertinent to decode the vast ocean of his knowledge.

NOTE

This chapter is a refined version of the Annual Ambedkar Memorial Lectures, delivered at the University of British Columbia and Simon Fraser University, Canada on 2 and 4 November 2017 respectively. Thanks are due to School of Public Policy and Global Affair, University of British Columbia and co-sponsors, Chetna Association of Canada, Dr. Hari Sharma Foundation, Department of Asian Studies at the University of British Columbia, The Robert H.N. Ho Family Foundation Program in Buddhism and Contemporary Society and the Institute for the Humanities at Simon Fraser University. A different version lecture was also delivered on the topic, ‘Decoding Ambedkar’s Ideas of Modernity and Nation Building’, at York Centre for Asian Research, 15 November 2017. Thanks are also due to the organizers.

REFERENCES

Ambedkar, B.R., 1979, Dr. Babasaheb Writings and Speeches, vol. 1, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1982, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 2, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1987(c), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 3. Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1987(e), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 4, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1989(b), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 5, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1989(c), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 6, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1990(b), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 8. Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1990(c), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 7, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1991(a), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 9, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1992, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 11, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1994, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 13, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1995, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 14 (I), Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 2003, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 17, Part III, Department Education, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

Anand, Mulk Raj, 1935, Untouchable, Wishart, London.

Anderson, Perry, 2012, The Indian Ideology, Three Essays Collective, Haryana.

Bourdieu, Pierre, 1986, ‘The Forms of Capital’ in J. Richardson, Handbook of Theory and Research for the Sociology of Education, Westport, CT, Greenwood.

Chandra, Bipan, et al., 1989, India’s Struggle for Independence (1897-1947), Penguin, New Delhi.

Freire, Paulo, 1970, Pedagogy of The Oppressed, Penguin Books, New Delhi.

Kumar, Vivek, 2002, Dalit Leadership in India, Kalpaz Publications, New Delhi.

——, 2005, ‘Situating Dalits in Indian Sociology’, Sociological Bulletin, vol. 54, no. 3, (pp. 514-32), New Delhi.

——, 2010, ‘Ambedkar’s Idea of Nation and Nation Building’, Journal of Human Rights Global Focus (pp. 69-85), International Human Foundation, Delhi.

——, 2013, ‘The New Dalit Diaspora: A Sociological Analysis’, in K.L. Sharma & Renuka Singh (eds.), Dual Identity: Indian Diaspora and Other Essays, Orient BlackSwan, New Delhi.

——, 2018, ‘Locating Dalit Perspective of Social Reality’, International Journal of Indigenous & Marginalized Affairs, vol. 4, no., 1, January-June, issue (pp. 57-78), New Delhi.

Kuhn, Thomas, 1970, The Structure of Scientific Revolution, The University of Chicago Press, Chicago, USA.

Lohia, Rammanohar, 1964, The Caste System, Rammanohar Lohia Samta Vidyalaya Nyas, Hyderabad.

Lucknann, Thomas & Peter L. Berger, 1967, ‘The Social Construction of Reality: A Treatise’ in The Sociology of Knowledge, Anchor Books, New York.

Mills, C.W., 1959, The Sociological Imagination, Oxford University Press, New York.

Roy, Arundhati (ed.), 2014, Annihilation of Caste, The Annotated Critical Edition, B.R. Ambedkar with an Introduction, ‘The Doctor and the Saint’, Navayana, New Delhi.

Shourie, Arun, 1997 (2012), Worshiping the False God: Ambedkar and the Fact which have been Erased, HarperCollins, New Delhi.

Singh, Ayodhya, 2003, Bharat Ka Mukti Samgram (Hindi), Granth Shilp (India) Private Limited, Delhi.

Zelliot, Eleanor, 1992, From Untouchable to Dalits and Other Essays, Manohar, New Delhi.

——, 2004, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar and the Untouchable Movement, Blumoon Books, New Delhi.

Zene, Cosima, 2013, The Political Philosophies of Antonia Gramsci and B.R. Ambedkar: Itineraries of Dalits and Subalterns, Routledge, New York.